[Music]
You are listening to Golden Rule Radio,
your weekly discussion of the precious
metals markets and the markets closely
associated with the metals. I'm Tori
alongside Miles and Rob, and together we
have over 75 years of experience
advising on and brokering the precious
metals. And each week, the three of us
provide you a technical analysis through
metals charts as well as cover the
underlying fundamentals and news that's
obviously helping to move and predict
the markets. And today we're going to
get into the week activity as well as
year-to-ate numbers. You know, this is
Golden Rule Radio and we will focus on
gold in every show, but today we're
going to bring a little platinum
discussion to the table as well as
getting into certainly the underlying
fundamentals that are moving the market
such as geopolitics for example. So
without further ado, Miles, how about a
weekly recap starting with gold? You got
to throw out the table a content story.
You just can't surprise people.
Excitedly surprised them in a few
minutes when we dive into platinum.
You're the guy that told the kid what
was in the birthday present, weren't
you? Yeah, we don't want him to switch
the channel, right? Okay, that's fair.
Yeah, cuz with the way Platinum's been
moving, I'm sure there's a lot of people
that might have questions. Although,
there might be a couple geopolitical
reasons why maybe we haven't been paying
as close attention to the market over
the last few days. So, yeah, I think we
got a lot to cover this week. So, let's
take a quick look at the metals and a
couple other market charts and what
we've seen here over the last 7 days.
So, we're looking at gold currently
sitting at $3,360.
We were up as much as 2% on the week.
So, we did have a little bit of movement
in the gold price, but here over the
last day, it's inched back down to kind
of right where we started. started about
3360 last Thursday and here we are
Wednesday afternoon at 3360 again.
Silver on the other hand up as much as
3% inch back down to 1% on the week now
but it's sitting at $36.70
and boy we really like that 37 number on
the silver chart. So we'll take a look
at that a little bit deeper here in a
moment. So far, that's been pretty tame.
But if we switch over to the big metals
topic this week, platinum. Platinum
currently up to $1,320.
That is a 6% move over the past week.
And we've seen a couple weeks here with
some pretty strong movement in platinum.
So, it's nice to see it's continuing
that trend as it's separating itself off
from its sister metal, palladium.
currently down at around $1,045
and palladium actually inched down over
the last week uh about 2% decline on the
palladium price. So the platinum to
palladium ratio is continuing to
separate itself. Quick look at the
equities market with the S&P still just
right at that 6,000 mark, 5,980.
[Music]
It's down 1% on the week. I just can't
quite get to the old highs, but it is
still trying to go that way. I'm
certainly very confident in the US stock
market, as you guys know, going forward.
No, I think there's a good chance we
still see the S&P inch up towards that
all-time high, but currently just
sitting a little bit below it. And
finally, the dollar is actually up a
little bit this week, sitting just under
99 on the dollar index, 98.8.
It's up half a point and doing me okay.
I mean, it's the dollar still below that
breakout floor point we talked about a
couple weeks ago, but it's definitely
hanging in there. Although, with
everything going on in the world, that
world reserve currency, you know, that
place that everybody in the world tends
to put money when things aren't looking
great, that's what do we call it? It's
um right on the tip of my tongue. Uh
could it be gold? Yeah, I you know, for
a second there I was thinking the world
reserve currency, but it seems like it
might be the shiny yellow metal that's
winning this fight this year. Well, all
the kids are talking about it. You know,
Gunlock and Paul Tudtor Jones, when you
listen to the big bond guys, they're
pointing to the bond market floundering
and they're saying, "Hey, you need to be
considering gold." And I'm hearing it so
much more on financial news pointing to
gold and silver beyond just the dollar
and the market. That's unusual. Really
unusual. I mean, especially you can say
that's probably the first time in your
decades of being with this company that
you've ever heard the Bond kings
speaking that way. Right. So, it is the
new Bond. We're not talking about a new
007 movie coming out. We're talking
about the new Flight to Quality asset.
Some people would say reduced risk or
what have you, but both of them too are
very bearish on the debt. Just like we
talked about Jaime Diamond from JP
Morgan talking about there's going to be
a break in the bond market and
everybody's going to panic. Well, now
you've got Jeffrey Gunlock and Paul
Tudtor Jones joining in. And Paul Tudtor
Jones said, "Look, we're in a debt
trap." And I think that's a huge reason
that you've seen central bank demand for
gold ramp up. And it's obviously a huge
reason why you're seeing the
ddollarization globally as an
alternative. It's not just US debt, but
dollar denominated assets. So, how did
he point the way forward? What's his
solution to the debt trap? You've got to
have negative real rates. What does that
mean? Well, to have negative real rates
means that you are returning less than
what you're gaining, obviously. So
inflation has to be higher than what you
can get on your return. So that's
inflating your way out of the problem
and that's strong for gold. We ended
last week saying that look as the debt
increases it gets more and more
expensive to pay off anyway. Then if you
have higher interest rates which the Fed
did not cut today
record on a Wednesday. So they've come
out and said we're still looking at two
rate cuts later in the year. Uh but they
didn't cut today. No. And they need more
data. They're always behind the curve.
And so anyway, to have negative real
rates means you're going to see rate
cuts. It means you're going to see
higher inflation. They're going to print
money. They're going to inflate their
way out of this issue. But they have to
stimulate. This administration, just
like President Trump was in his first
term, very, very stimulative, which is
why gold went up over 65% in his first
term. Nothing new under the sun here.
But the world moves to gold as a
monetary metal. The white metals are
industrial metals more than they are
monetary metals. Platinum has no
monetary metal component. So you see
gold and silver down today with a dollar
climb, but you don't see platinum down.
No. Because it's its own market and it's
not going to be platinum that central
banks are turning to. No, they need as
many ounces as possible. And here's
actually a good image on why that is.
because the global value of gold is
dwarfing the global value of silver and
certainly the global value of platinum.
So the global gold value stands at 23.1
trillion whereas silver it's only 340.5
billion. So the above ground Oh yeah the
above ground supply which is why you see
these massive spikes in the white
metals. Well platinum is 3.8 8 billion.
So compare 3.8 billion for a market in a
commodity to 23 trillion. And now you
see why with the money supply being what
it is, why the banks lean on gold and
why it's actually able to compete with
the bond market. But you also see
opportunities in the white metals that
people are starting to take advantage
of. Well, yeah. I mean, that's a great
part of why we diversify. Y this is
something that gets right into our ratio
trading. It gets even into premium
swapping because supply and demand in
that market on such a smaller market,
you can see premium spike in silver far
greater than you do in gold. Yeah. Well,
it's been a running theme of ours over
the last couple weeks. And I think when
you bring in guys like Gunlock and Jamie
Diamond, and you start to realize that
the big boys see the writing on the wall
with what's going on in the bond market,
which is the most important market in
the world. And the reaction to that on a
eastern or corporate or central bank or
even now a western corporate and western
central bank transition
out of US dollar denominated assets and
we've seen Rob how terrible has the bond
sales been over the last 6 months. So
not great. We're seeing this transition
over to things like precious metals. And
lo and behold, we're looking at gold
going from what low 2000s to the mid
3000s in about a year. What you guys are
now starting to see is we're starting to
see as the retail investor gets involved
into the market, the retail investor is
going to reply to the rise in the price
of gold by looking for cheaper
alternatives. So, we've talked about
this for years. Gold always moves first
because gold is bought by big investors
on the hundreds of millions or billion
scale. That's why you're looking at a
global market in the trillions and then
the rest of us following around on the
coattails are going to move into the
less expensive alternatives like silver.
There's a reason it's been called the
poor man's gold forever. Forever. But
you know, one thing too I want to
interject. The bond market is three to
four times the size of the stock market.
Yep. And people are focused on the stock
market because that's what's put in
front of them every night on the news.
But at the same time, when you talk to a
financial advisor and you say, "Well,
how do I protect myself from say a
fallout in the stock market? If equities
were to drop, what do I do?" What's been
their solution, Tori? Well, buy bonds.
Buy bonds. That's the hedge. That's been
the flight to safety or flight to
quality, right? And they'll tell you,
well, you're 70% equities and 30% in
bonds or 50/50. That's more
conservative, but not according to Jamie
Diamond, not according to Paul Tudtor
Jones. Well, certainly not going
forward. I mean, their warning signs are
for going forward. But you can look back
and a position of gold in your portfolio
far outperforms a bond position for the
last 25 years. The problem is a lot of
financial adviserss or money managers
aren't going to get paid to manage your
physical gold position. It kind of is
out there where nobody can see it. And
so there tends to be a bias or sometimes
there's an ignorance. And I don't mean
that from a slanderous standpoint. I
just mean look gold averages 8 12%
return a year over the last 40 years 50
years find that in a bond return and it
provides that downside protection. So
the draw down on your portfolio when the
stocks actually do end up seeing those
major pullbacks. Gold is a much better
hedge than the bonds have been. And now
we're talking about going forward these
guys are all in on the gold and they're
bond market experts. Let's say there is
a dramatic drop in the stock market.
Let's say the Dow loses 10,000 points in
a matter of a couple of weeks. You'll
see gold fall in sympathy as people are
trying to cover their debt positions,
their leverage. But every time we have
seen something dramatic happen in the
stock market, go back to the 2008 2009
drop in the market. Gold fell from its
high within six weeks. the physical
price of a Kruegerand was back above
where gold had started before the drop
in the stock market. Saw the same thing
in the co crash. But it didn't take six
weeks that time. It took barely six
days. Yeah. And I think now with gold
moving into the mind of the global
investor, the big players, central
banks, etc. I think you could see gold
fall in sympathy very briefly, but those
days are gone. Well, Miles, let's come
back to silver because you mentioned
something about it being the poor man's
gold. It is indicative to me of a
western buying phenomenon. So, the gold
has been this eastern buying, central
bank buying, large institutional money.
So, now we're seeing silver's resurgence
and in fact the futures market, you're
seeing a lot of longs from the
commitment of traders report. The shorts
are starting to get swallowed up and
you've got more and more longs going
here. And the reason I'm coming back to
that, Miles, is you mentioned the $37
figure in your weekly recap. Yeah, let's
go back to that. And I'm not the only
one. I've heard a number of people in
the charting world over the last couple
of years talking about the importance of
$35
in silver. And it's not surprising to me
how quickly when we finally broke it
that we just pushed right through it. I
mean, we tapped it in September, October
of last year with a decline.
tapped it again in March and then when
we finally blew through it, it came
through with a vengeance. The reason
that number matters is, believe it or
not, you can actually go back 10 or 15
years on the chart and you can see what
kind of activity or action took place
around certain price levels and why.
What are the types of things that are
going to cause people to make a buy or
sell transaction given a certain price
and extrapolate that out into the
future? So, you're looking at a lot of
trading volatility at the previous end
of the last bull market where we saw a
significant swing between about 25 and
40 back and forth and a couple of tops
right there around 35. and then the
final breakdown below 35. So, it wasn't
surprising at all that we saw a
significant move above 35 and now we're
really getting into last bull market top
territory. Anybody who's been listening
to our show for the last couple of
years, this is the same conversation we
had back when gold was bumping around
1900. It's the exact same conversation.
you're going to see some resistance in
that range in that like 16 to$,900 range
in gold. For silver, it's 35 to4 or $45
range. But ultimately, there's nothing
that's really going to turn silver down.
It's more just an issue of is this
something that ends up happening over
the next 3 to 6 months or over the next
2 or 3 years. And that's the part that
you kind of don't know. As a chart guy,
I'd much rather go for two to three
years because the longer it takes to
happen, the higher the end number will
end up being down the road. But
ultimately, the speed at which gold is
taking off and some of the other things
we're seeing here in the markets, I
wouldn't be surprised to see silver have
a pretty rapid catchup at least here
where we see the gold to silver ratio,
which got as high as 100 to one here
recently. 104. Yeah. uh not snap all the
way down to like 35. You know, I'm not
talking about the big swing, but easily
see that ratio come back down into maybe
the 60s, even the 50s, and just catch
back up, not with ultimately where it's
going to end, but just with what gold
has done so far, cuz we know that the
bull market in metals will continue
until some sort of fiscal responsibility
takes place or gold extends to such an
overpriced level like it did in 2011
that it's going to have to come back
down because gold is actually overpriced
which we're nowhere near at this point.
No. So ultimately in the midst of that,
let's remember that markets do what
markets do. Silver short-term is
overbought now at this point. We've got
some pretty significant divergence in
RSI. It's well above its moving
averages. There's some fibs starting to
present themselves. Could silver go from
37 down to 30 and then keep climbing
from there? Absolutely. So, I'm not
saying that's going to happen. I just am
always trying to encourage our
listeners, our clients, anybody who does
any trading market swing, have some
patience and know what the long game is
on something like this. I like that
focus on the ratio, too, because getting
in at 100 to1, we're telling our
clients, we're advising a heavier silver
position than usual. Yep. It's something
that's a no-brainer. And then if you do
see it come down into 60 or 70, well,
we're exiting a lot of that silver and
swapping into gold. And it's like having
purchased gold at a 20% discount. And
so, anybody that's been nervous about
acquiring gold at too high of a price,
it's still undervalued right now. If you
look at silver, don't be afraid of
bumping our head up on these resistance
points to the upside like 38. I'll
attest to the fact it's not been months,
it's been years that you have said we're
going to have a hard time breaking
through 35. When we do, we're going to
run unchecked to around 38 and then
we'll pause and then it's going to be 40
as the new target. If we break above
that, things get real exciting for that
$50 figure. But on the downside here,
you mentioned coming down maybe even to
30. Don't you think that 35 being that
old really tough ceiling to break
through because question
that's now the new floor? I think that's
a great question. Maybe you don't really
know until it gets there. The floor will
create itself. I just pulled 30 out cuz
30 is a round number. That wasn't
something off a chart. I was just
explaining a concept. So, it certainly
could. I don't like to predict where
something may place its foot down on the
next step. As long as the next step is
higher than the last step, that's all I
really care about. So,
so if the last step was $29, as long as
it's above 29, I'm happy with that.
Let's keep going with the white metals,
guys, because we keep saying we're going
to talk about it. My lord, since we've
been talking, platinum is now back up
over 1300 again. So, that's nice. 1310.
Platinum is on a tear and platinum is
actually flirting with the previous high
going back to February. So, believe it
or not, despite all the growth we've had
in platinum here, platinum is still
arguably and technically in a big
trading range. We're right at the
breakout point for platinum. This is
going to be the floor from the previous
high. So if you figured the previous
high was in the 22 $2,300 range, we had
an immediate crash and a bounce. And
then platinum traded between about 1300
and uh most of the time was spent
between like 1300 maybe 1,600ish before
it finally broke down. So we're right at
the bottom of the old trading range. And
honestly, a push inside of let's say
1350, I think it's very likely you could
see platinum either trade up to or
quickly run as high as like,900
on this move just based on where some of
the previous trading in the ranges took
place. So, the run in platinum, while it
feels big thus far, it ain't nothing
yet. Yeah, it's just playing catchup.
Well, and it did have a lot of catch-up.
There's been a lot of patience on the
part of the platinum owner, right? I
mean, just had a call I had a call
Monday. Sam bought platinum from me 12
years ago and he calls me. He's like,
"All right, sell all my platinum." I'm
like, "Sam, we just got here." Yeah, we
just started, man.
He's like, "Yeah, but I've got a limited
horizon, Rob. I'm 80 years old." I'm
like, "Well, give me another week."
Okay, Sam. Just give me one more week.
Let's see what platinum can do. Well, I
mean, you could have bought Platinum for
850 bucks in 2008. Yeah. And then again
in 2016. Oh, he did. He's in the 800s.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And then he in 2023.
Yeah. Well, and again in March of 2025
is
he just like finally after all this time
I can turn a profit. I get it. I get it.
Right. And this is when it's hard to
hold it because you get exhausted, you
get worn out from it. But we tend to cap
our platinum positions like in IRA and
otherwise 5 10 15% ceiling. Yeah. It's a
speculative small little venture if you
will, but this is why we diversify
because here is an example not just
today, but platinum's up 4.5% today with
gold and silver down. So we talk about
minimizing the draw down on your
portfolio. Your precious metals
portfolio needs to be diversified too
between bullion and semi- numismatic,
between gold and silver, between
platinum and platium or platinum and
gold and silver. You can buy silver
dollars. You can buy 80 to 100y old
silver dollars cheaper than 100 ounce
bars right now. Incredible. Which have
you ever seen that in your 40 plus
years? No. No. Never. The older peace
and Morgan dollars. So, it's a really
fun market dynamic. But after 15 years
of stagnation in platinum, I understand
that. But you guys remember it's 30
times rarer than gold. How many times
have we seen it not only equal to the
price of gold, but two or three times
the price of gold. Exactly. Look at this
long-term image where we're not
expecting to go back to a day and age
where it was five times the price of
gold. But here, platinum has been a
third of the price of gold. Which means
for every ounce of platinum that we
bought at that level, if they just get
to par with each other, that means 3
ounces of platinum trade straight across
for 3 ounces of gold instead of 3 ounces
of platinum equaling 1 oz of gold.
That's a major ratio trade. Major. And
platinum is hard to predict because most
of its applications are in the
automotive industry. It makes up 37% of
the demand and then 30% is industrial.
Jewelry use, yes, but this isn't the
market that really sucks it up. We need
the industrial demand to ramp up and
especially as things get geopolitically
tense in Russia, in South Africa. That's
the majority of that market, 80%. Yeah.
If you want a really great article,
reach out to us and we can feed you an
excellent update on why platinum and why
we're recommending that that remain a
part of your portfolio right now if this
part hasn't made sense. So guys, before
we wrap up, let's just do a real quick
recap of what's going on fundamentally.
We've talked a lot about charts, but
certainly we've got international
geopolitics at the forefront here with
Israel and Iran. every time we get a
ramp up in tensions, gold is going to
react or at least not decline when
there's other news that would otherwise
have gold come down. But, you know,
Iran's part of the so-called crink group
with China and Russia and North Korea
and there's obviously starkly different
ideologies and we'll see what's
happening. It's even causing a
Washington divide. It's causing a global
divide. It's just the latest at the
forefront. But it's more than that, too.
We've got continued economic data that's
mixed. We'll get good news on CPI and
inflation, then turn around and got bad
news on expected CPI and inflation
moving forward. So, the markets really
don't know what to do. And when there's
uncertainty, gold does well and I think
that that's continuing to keep wind in
the sales of gold as that monetary metal
and unpredictably also what direction
the US dollar is going. Yeah. Typically,
seasonally, gold is soft in the summer.
It doesn't look like that's going to be
the case this year. It does not. That's
going to do it this week for Golden Rule
Radio. As always, we appreciate you
stopping by. If you liked what you
heard, we encourage you to swing on by
our website at mlveni.com. That's
mcvy.com.
You can also find us on Twitter at a
gold and Facebook at Melvin Financial.
And as always, if you'd like to give us
a call, we're happy to talk with you
about your personal precious metals
portfolio. You can reach us at 1
800-5259556.
Thanks again for listening and have a
great week.
[Music]